<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Church-customes vindicated in tvvo sermons preached at Kingstone upon Thames: the one at the primary visitation of the Right Reverend Father in God Richard by the grace of God late L.B. of Winton, anno 1628. The other at the first metropoliticall visitation of the Most Reverend Father in God William by the grace of God Lord Arch-Bishop of Canterbury his grace, &amp;c. July 9. 1635. By William Quelch B.D. and R. of East-horsly Surrey.</title>
            <author>Quelch, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850706</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850706</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10268)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1253:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Church-customes vindicated in tvvo sermons preached at Kingstone upon Thames: the one at the primary visitation of the Right Reverend Father in God Richard by the grace of God late L.B. of Winton, anno 1628. The other at the first metropoliticall visitation of the Most Reverend Father in God William by the grace of God Lord Arch-Bishop of Canterbury his grace, &amp;c. July 9. 1635. By William Quelch B.D. and R. of East-horsly Surrey.</title>
                  <author>Quelch, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M[iles] F[lesher] for Nathaniel Butter neare S. Austins Gate at the signe of the Pyde Bull,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15930:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHVRCH-CVSTOMES VINDICATED: IN TWO SERMONS PREACHED AT <hi>Kingstone</hi> upon <hi>Thames:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>THE ONE</hi> At the <hi>Primary Viſitation</hi> of the Right Reverend Father in God RICHARD by the grace of God late <hi>L. B.</hi> of <hi>Winton, Anno</hi> 1628.</p>
            <p>THE OTHER At the <hi>firſt Metropoliticall Viſitation</hi> of the Moſt Reverend Father in God WILLIAM by the grace of God <hi>Lord Arch Biſhop of Canterbury</hi> his <hi>Grace, &amp;c.</hi> July 9. 1635.</p>
            <p>BY WILLIAM QUELCH B. D. and <hi>R.</hi> of <hi>Eaſt-horſly</hi> SURREY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM: 16.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Now I beſeech you brethren, marke them which cauſe diviſions, and offences contrary to the doctrine which you have received, and avoid them, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> neare S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Gate at the Signe of the <hi>Pyde Bull.</hi> 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15930:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15930:2"/>
            <head>To the courteous Readers, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially my Brethren of the CLERGIE;</head>
            <head type="sub">Peace be multiplyed, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or this end I firſt ſet upon this worke; and for the ſame I thought good to ſet it forth: had it found the effect of my firſt deſire; I had never thought of a ſecond publication: But when I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood upon later experience, by the frivolous exceptions caſt out againſt me, how much I had failed of my expectation, I knew not which way to come off from private cenſure, unleſſe I ſhould put my ſelfe and my poor endevors upon the tryall of publique cenſure.</p>
            <p>To hear of <hi>contentions</hi> breaking out againſt the <hi>cuſtomes of the Church</hi> is no news at all,
<pb facs="tcp:15930:3"/>neither muſt it ſtumble us:<note place="margin">Ver. 19.</note> he that for the <hi>tryall of his children</hi> ſuffers <hi>hereſie,</hi> hath his ends in the leaſt and ſmalleſt oppoſitions: and if it be the will and pleaſure of God, by the light skirmiſhes of ſome few to bring to paſſe a greater good, I ſhall learne to magnify the wiſedome of the Almighty, that turns the cavills of contentious men to the further enlargement of his glory. Howſoever it be, thou haſt the ſame that was firſt delivered, nothing is altered but the outward dreſſe, much leſſe any word or ſentence changed, which I could heare was ſubject to exception. If thou light upon any thing worth the reading, thank not me for my good will, who never intended to make it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, but thank the ill will of thoſe carping hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, who put me upon it in mine owne defence, and thinke of me as of the pooreſt unworthy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt Ieſus, who ſhall be ever ready upon all occaſions to approve my ſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, in all Chriſtian offices to be commanded,</hi> W. Q.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:15930:3"/>
            <p>PErlegi has duas Conciones <hi>in 1. Ep. ad Cor. Cap. 11. ver. 16.</hi> in quibus nihil reperio ſanae doctrinae, aut bonis moribus contrarium, quominus cum utilitate publicâ imprimantur, ita tamen, ut ſi non intra quinque menſes proximè ſequentes typis mandentur, haec licentia ſit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex Aedibus Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethanis <date>14. Cal. Martii.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>GUIL. BRAY R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. P. &amp; D. D. Arch. Cant. Sacel. Domeſticus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15930:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15930:4"/>
            <head>CHVRCH-CVSTOMES VINDICATED.</head>
            <head type="sub">The firſt Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 11.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If any man luſt to bee contentious, Wee have no ſuch Cuſtome, nor the Churches of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> through the ſtubborne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of <hi>contentious men,</hi> are growne ſo obſolete and out of <hi>cuſtome</hi> in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that I feare I may bee thought to breake the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> while I ſeeke to vindicate and defend her <hi>cuſtomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15930:5"/>
But when I looke back unto purer times, and finde how the <hi>Church</hi> could ſtand upon her <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> in the very infancy and childhood of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Aetatem habet, Ipſu interrogate. <hi>Ioh. 9.23.</hi>
               </note> before the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> were come to age, I make no doubt but the ſame <hi>cuſtoms</hi> being grown at length to mans eſtate, in the ripeneſſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity of the <hi>Church,</hi> may now have leave to ſpeak for themſelves, at leaſt in their owne defence. <hi>Si quis videtur contentioſus;</hi> If any ſeeme, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contentions</hi> and <hi>cuſtomes</hi> appeare unto us at the firſt ſight like two ſturdy and valiant Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ready to aſſault each other in a ſingle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat: <hi>Contention</hi> ſtands up like proud <hi>Goliah,</hi> ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and powting againſt all the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of the <hi>Churches.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>Cuſtome</hi> ſtands up like little <hi>David</hi> to accept the challenge of <hi>Contention,</hi> and bids de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to the proud Philiſtime.</p>
            <p>Upon the iſſue of this Skirmiſh hangs all the peace and liberty of the <hi>Church:</hi> for if <hi>Contention</hi> win the day, and chance to prove maiſter of the field, then farewell the <hi>Church</hi> and all her <hi>cuſtomes;</hi> but if the <hi>Church</hi> prevaile and get the maiſtery, then downe the winde goes <hi>contention,</hi> and down goe they that <hi>love contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You would be glad I trow to ſee the iſſue of this battell, ſtay but a while and ſtand your ground; and when the Philiſtime hath brav'd himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the armies of the living God, you ſhall ſee how little <hi>David</hi> ſhall knock him downe, as it were with a ſtone taken from the <hi>Churches Scrip. Non habemus conſuetudinem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diviſ.</note> We have &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contention</hi> is the firſt that makes the challenge,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15930:5"/>and if you deſire to know the ground of this dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quarrell; you muſt be pleaſed to conſider three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Time and place where the quarrell firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and that was <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in the <hi>Church;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in the <hi>Church of Corinth;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in her yong dayes, when S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe was yet alive.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The nature, and quality of this <hi>contention:</hi> for it was a poore and ſlender quarrell againſt a Ceremony, and no more.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By whom the quarrell was begun, and that's implied here, to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome buſie fellow of a wrangling humour, that <hi>loved contention</hi> more then peace.</p>
            <p>Loe this you have for the notifying of <hi>contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and then for the <hi>Churches-cuſtomes</hi> you have three like circumſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The nature and quality of the <hi>cuſtomes,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for wee muſt not ſtand upon every <hi>cuſtome,</hi> but upon a decent and reverend <hi>cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Who they are that maintaine the <hi>cuſtomes;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> noted here to be <hi>Churches</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Who were the founders of the <hi>cuſtomes;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and they are implyed here to bee the Apoſtles of Chriſt that could not erre in doctrine, much leſſe in the ordination of a <hi>cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the chief heads both of this <hi>cuſtome,</hi> and of that <hi>contention;</hi> and when I ſhall come in the end to compare them both together, and to <hi>lay mouth to mouth, eyes to eyes, and hands to hands:</hi> I meane ſuch a grave and decent <hi>cuſtome,</hi> againſt ſuch a ſlight and trifling <hi>quarrell:</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">Kings 4.34.</note> the <hi>Churches</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15930:6"/>of God that kept the <hi>cuſtome</hi> againſt that one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>Church</hi> that broke the <hi>cuſtome:3</hi> the Apoſtles of Chriſt the founders of this <hi>cuſtome,</hi> againſt that <hi>one contentious man,</hi> the ringleader and broacher of innovation; I ſhall thinke it fit to refer the cauſe to your own judgement, whether ye thinke ſuch <hi>a cuſtome</hi> maintained by all the <hi>Churches,</hi> and allowed by the warrant of the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> be not worthy to beate downe ſuch a fond and frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>quarrell</hi> but newly brought into the <hi>Church of Corinth,</hi> by that filly ſect-maſter that ſtands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record for a <hi>contentious man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all theſe I ſhall have faire occaſion to ſpeak ſomething.</p>
            <p>And firſt I muſt begin to deale with <hi>contention,</hi> a troubleſome and turbulent ſpirit I am like to finde him,<note place="margin">Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what it is.</note> that loves wrangling as hee loves his life, and can no more bee tyed to any good order, then the waters of <hi>Nyle</hi> to the banks of their own channell.</p>
            <p>He never appeares to us in a ſtill voice, as the Lord appeared unto <hi>Eliah;</hi> but whenſoever he comes, he comes in a tempeſt, ſtorming and blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering againſt all good order, both of <hi>Church</hi> and State: Did you ever heare the pedigree of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention?</hi> There was a baſtard begotten by anger, nurſed by pride, and maintained by wilfull contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and when they came to give him a name, they beſtowed upon him the name of <hi>Contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As was the name of the childe ſo was his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for a ſoone as ever hee began to goe, hee went backward like the Sea-crab: as ſoon as ever
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15930:6"/>he began to read, he read backward like the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes: as ſoone as ever hee began to row, hee rowed backward evermore, againſt tide &amp; ſtream.</p>
            <p>Pitty ſuch a croſſe, diſorderly mate ſhould finde harbour in any civill ſociety,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.3.</note> much leſſe in the <hi>Church</hi> of God, which ought to be compoſed <hi>as a City at unity.</hi> If <hi>contention</hi> muſt needs bee, let it bee ſent to Bedlem, or Pariſ-garden where it may converſe with none but dogs and Beares, or men more wilde then thoſe ſalvage creatures; never let it enter into Gods inheritance, leſt the fiends of hell take more delight in the quarrels of Gods people, then men are wont to fancy to themſelves when they ſee the quarrells of dogs and beares.</p>
            <p>It were to bee wiſhed that theſe diſcords of ſchiſme and diſſention, that make muſicke onely for the devill, may never be heard in the Church of God: but I feare me as long as the Church conſiſts of men, and men conſiſt of ſundry paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we ſhall hardly be free from all <hi>contention.</hi> The devill is growne ſuch a cunning politician, that when he cannot rob us of our truth, hee will doe the beſt he can to rob us of our peace; and when hee cannot plucke up the good <hi>wheat</hi> of <hi>wholeſome doctrine</hi> that is ſowne in our field by the <hi>good ſeeds-man,</hi> he does all that he can to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle the <hi>wheat</hi> with the <hi>tares</hi> and <hi>darnell</hi> of <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. epiſt. 48.</hi> Neque propter pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am domini, neque prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter piſces malos rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus retia.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And what though? ſhall we therefore forſake the <hi>good field,</hi> and renounce the <hi>wheat</hi> of <hi>whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine</hi> becauſe wee finde it mingled with <hi>ſome cockle?</hi> Shall wee forſake the <hi>Church,</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15930:7"/>ſhipwrack the faith, and caſt off the truth, becauſe we cannot have it cleane from all kinde of weeds? Nay rather, if we may have the word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as ſo cheape a rate, and pay nothing for it but a little <hi>contention,</hi> let us never complaine of a deare bargaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contention</hi> hath beene and will ever be the unwelcome companion of the <hi>Church militant:</hi> Chriſt himſelfe came not into the world to bring <hi>peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath ever beene in all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> but to bring a <hi>ſword:</hi> and if any <hi>Church</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth can ſhew me a perfect charter of exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from all <hi>contention,</hi> I ſhould begin to thinke that wee had our heaven already upon earth, and that the <hi>militant Church</hi> were turned <hi>triumphant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take a ſhort ſurvey of all the Churches, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jewiſh or Chriſtian, Eaſterne or Weſterne, ancient or moderne; and you ſhall not finde any one of them that ever could free themſelves from <hi>this eating</hi> gangrene of <hi>contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure the Jewiſh Church had no ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge: for as long as ſhe ſwarmed with ſundry ſects of Phariſees, and Sadduces, &amp; Eſſens, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodians, and Hemerobaptiſts,<note place="margin">In the Iewiſh Church. Vid. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph.</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit. <hi>lib. 13. Philo Iud. Euſeb.</hi> &amp; aliot. In the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Chur:</note> and Samaritans, and I know not what, that differed both in courſe of life, and point of beliefe, how could ſhee bee free from all <hi>contentions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may bee in the Chriſtian Church there was no <hi>contention</hi> for all that: No? does <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> reckon up no leſſe then foureſcore hereſies raging in the <hi>Church</hi> of God like the Bulls of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan, and ſhall we beleeve there was no <hi>contention</hi> all that while?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15930:7"/>
But, ſay they had ſome <hi>contentions</hi> in thoſe times betwixt the Orthodox and the heretickes, yet I hope among the Orthodox themſelves there was perfect union. But whatſoever you may think of thoſe times, as if they had reſt from all <hi>contention;</hi> yet if you knew the differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the beſt learned of thoſe ages: (.i.) <hi>Anice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Polycarpus, Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">apud Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. eccl: hiſt. lib. 5. cap. 24. Hieron. part. 1. tract. 3. ep. 36, 37. &amp;c. Ep. Caeleſ. pap. ad quoſdam Galliarum epiſcopos.</note> 
               <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> and <hi>Ruffinus, Stephanus</hi> and <hi>Cyprian, Victor</hi> and the Eaſterne <hi>Churches, Proſper</hi> and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of France, and many hundreds more that might be named; you would ſoone beleeve that the <hi>Churches</hi> in their times could hardly bee free from all <hi>contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if <hi>contention</hi> crept into the <hi>Church</hi> in after ages, yet I hope in the Apoſtles time, and the <hi>Churches</hi> planted by their hands, we ſhall not heare of the leaſt murmuring, or whiſpering of <hi>contention:</hi> Surely if ever the <hi>Church</hi> were free from all <hi>contention,</hi> it is moſt like to be in thoſe dayes of innocence; and yet if you look into 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> of this our <hi>Epiſt.</hi> and the 11. <hi>ver.</hi> yee ſhall heare S. <hi>Paul</hi> complaine of ſome <hi>contentions: It is reported to me by thoſe of the houſe of Cloe, that there are contentions among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To heare of <hi>contentions</hi> among the members of the Church was a ſmall matter: but if you looke into the 22. <hi>Cap.</hi> of S. <hi>Luke ver.</hi> 24.<note place="margin">Among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> you ſhall heare of <hi>contention</hi> among the Apoſtles themſelves; and if you looke into the 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> you ſhall heare of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tention</hi> among the chiefe pillars of the <hi>Church,</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and that about no meane point of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15930:8"/>Chriſtian politie, that concerned the abrogation of Jewiſh Ceremonies.<note place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>1.</hi> tom. cont. <hi>4.</hi> lib <hi>4.</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet. &amp; alii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It makes mee wonder ſo much the more why the Church of Rome at this day ſhould ſtand ſo much upon the <hi>unitie of the Church,</hi> and beare us in hand that <hi>their unity and concord in religion is a certaine badge and character of the true Church.</hi> They have found that pearle it ſeems in the <hi>field</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> which could never bee found in former ages; and though we ſell all that we have, like the <hi>good Merchant in the Goſpell,</hi> to get poſſeſſion of that pearle, they will make us beleeve we ſhall be gainers by the bargaine.</p>
            <p>It is a good purchaſe indeed to buy truth at what rate ſoever, but to buy truth attended with unitie, were a purchaſe in my minde beyond the rules of Numeration.</p>
            <p>But is this purchaſe to be had at Rome? Yes ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>for all the members of their Church are ſo colligated and bound together in a kinde of ſubjection and ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to one head,</hi> that you ſhall ſeldome heare of any <hi>contention</hi> among them that ever breakes out into open flames.</p>
            <p>A happy <hi>Church</hi> they muſt needs have, if things be anſwerable to their vaunts, but if it doe not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare upon juſt triall out of the beſt Records of their owne <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Halls</hi> diſſwaſive from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</note> that they have <hi>contentions</hi> as well as wee, as great as ours, as loud as ours; I ſhall be ready to ſubſcribe to the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome, and returne againe to her communion.</p>
            <p>Did you never heare of any difference betwixt the <hi>Thomiſts</hi> and the <hi>Scotiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the Church of Rome.</note> of any jarres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15930:8"/>the <hi>Seculars</hi> and the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> of any quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells among the Cardinalls themſelves in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred conclave? what <hi>Church,</hi> what State in the whole world that is not conſcious of their diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? and if all theſe be not proof enough that their peace comes ſhort of ours, their diſſention is more then ours, let us appeale to <hi>Bellarmine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the chiefe Advocate of the Romane cauſe, who reckons us more then 200 opinions diverſly maintained <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> among the Doctors of their <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A goodly unity I durſt to warrant you that ſhines in the midſt of ſo many quarrells, and a goodly <hi>Church</hi> by the ſame reaſon that muſt be knowne by this jarring unity: if they have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter badge and livery of their <hi>Church</hi> then ſuch a counterfeit pretended unity, we ſhall never have cauſe I dare ſay either to be fond of their <hi>church,</hi> or to be jealous of our own.</p>
            <p>And yet tis a wonder to ſee with what a face of braſſe and impudence the Romaniſts of theſe times are wont to upbraid us with the quarrells of our <hi>Church,</hi> as if Rome had engroſſed all the unity: Your <hi>Church,</hi> ſay they,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pacianus citat. à Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus (inquit) eſt mihi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Cat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus cegno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Ierom. cont. Lucifer. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em.</note> what is it but a beaſt of many heads, patched up with divers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry factions, while one adheres to <hi>Luther,</hi> another to <hi>Calvin,</hi> a third to <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> another to <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> as if we delighted more to be called from names of men, then to be called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from the name of Chriſt, or <hi>Catholiques</hi> from the faith profeſſed by them.</p>
            <p>For our parts be it knowne to all the world
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15930:9"/>we hate to be called from the name of any man be he what he will, yea though it be the name of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> we are free enough from thoſe <hi>contentions</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> imputes to this <hi>Church of Corinth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.11 12, 13.</note> and though they impute unto us any other differences which have been alwaies inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the pureſt <hi>Churches,</hi> they muſt not think to ſhake our faith by ſuch poore and ſlender ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrations.</p>
            <p>We know that theſe were the common darts which both the Heathens of old, and the Turks of latter times were wont to caſt againſt the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt:</hi> in Act. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hom. <hi>33.</hi> et in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od Gal. <hi>Cypr:</hi> de unitate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Celſus apud Origen. lib. cont. Celſum Cortugal. orat. habit. Rhod.</note> and if they can find no other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to confute us, but what they are faine to borrow from <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> and ſuch as equally concern both them and us, they will make us think they are hardly driven.</p>
            <p>Let them free themſelves from their own <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,</hi> and then they may the better object ours; in the meane while as long as we ſee no other remedy, we will ſet us down by the <hi>Church of Corinth,</hi> and patiently beare both her lot and ours.</p>
            <p>We can hardly look to be in better ſtate then the Apoſtolique <hi>Churches,</hi> and if they were faine to ſuffer <hi>contention,</hi> why ſhould we grudge to bear the like? our caſe can hardly be worſe then theirs, for they had <hi>contentions in this ver. ſchiſmes in the</hi> 18. <hi>ver. hereſies in the</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> and therefore if all theſe ſhould fall to our lott, (which God of his mercy turne away from us) yet we have learned of the bleſſed Apoſtle not to <hi>think ſtrange of any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15930:9"/>ſuch tryall,</hi> as if <hi>ſome new thing were fallen</hi> upon us, but patiently to ſhare in that common calamity that equally belongs to all the <hi>Churches.</hi> When all is done, the <hi>Church of Corinth</hi> ſhall be our apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, we ſuffer no more then ſhe hath done, and ſeeing we are joyned with her in the ſame cauſe, let us make enquirie a little further, and perhaps we ſhall match her ſomewhat nearer in the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ground and reaſon of <hi>contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though every <hi>Church</hi> hath ſome <hi>contention,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ceremony</note> yet every <hi>Church</hi> hath not the ſame. There is a (<hi>talis</hi>) for <hi>contention</hi> as well as for <hi>cuſtome;</hi> for one is like the Palmer-worme that eates nothing but the leaves: another like the Caterpillar that deſtroys the fruit: and another like the Canker that devoures the body of religion. Some quarrels are but light and gentle waves that dally and play with the ſhip of Chriſt; others are proud and lofty ſurges that crack the cordage of the ſhip;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Leve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> undae. <hi>2</hi> Majora volumina. <hi>3</hi> Ignei glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi.</note> and ſome are fiery balls that aſcend to heaven, and threaten the ſafety of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all the quarrells that ever were moved in the <hi>Church,</hi> you will think that this in my text was one of the leaſt: Nothing was oppoſed, for for ought we find, but a bare ceremony, and the outward geſture in praying or propheſying was the onely cauſe of this ſharp <hi>contention.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. ver. 2. &amp; 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A poore occaſion to make a difference when they were agreed upon the ſubſtance: yet conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering withall what miſchiefe may grow upon the <hi>Church</hi> by the leaſt quarrell once begun, the Apoſtle thinks it meet to beſtir himſelfe, and to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15930:10"/>quench the fire of <hi>contention,</hi> that it may not break out into greater flames.</p>
            <p>Our wiſe Apoſtle was not to learne that a ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of it ſelfe was of little reckoning, but when a ceremony is enjoyned by lawfull autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,<note place="margin">Quod mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt, minimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, ſed in mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo, te fidele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſemagnum eſt. <hi>Aug. de doct. Chri. lib. 4.</hi>
               </note> he knew well enough that <hi>obedience or diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in a ſmall matter was not to be counted a ſmall matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is the ſame reaſon of obedience or diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, whether in ſmaller or in greater mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: for tis not the thing commanded that binds the conſcience, but the power from whence the commandement comes; be the thing commanded never ſo great, it commends the obedience never the more: be the thing commanded never ſo ſmall, it cannot excuſe the diſobedience.</p>
            <p>Chriſt commends the good ſervant becauſe he was <hi>faithfull in the leaſt things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.25</note> to teach us that faithfulneſſe or unfaithfulneſſe in the leaſt things cannot be counted the leaſt thing: well may the leaſt things aggravate the unfaithfulneſſe, but I am ſure of that they cannot excuſe it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Lord himſelfe doth often puniſh the leaſt unfaithfulneſſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16, 17. Num. 15.32.</note> whether <hi>in eating an apple,</hi> or <hi>gathering of ſticks</hi> when tis forbidden, with greater puniſhments then fouler ſins, becauſe it proceeds from meere wilfulneſſe: ſo the Apoſtles of Chriſt and their lawfull ſucceſſors may ſafely puniſh the leaſt <hi>contention</hi> againſt a ceremony, when they ſee it proceeds from meere ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as well as ſome greater and fouler ſins that ſpring from weakneſſe and infirmity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15930:10"/>
More danger there is in this poore <hi>contention</hi> then the common ſort of men doe commonly think,<note place="margin">The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntention <hi>Pro. 18.19.</hi>
               </note> not onely becauſe it kindles a fire among brethren of the ſam faith and the ſame religion, whoſe aemulous vyings and mutuall conteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among themſelves cannot chuſe but aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and increaſe the flame, but alſo becauſe tis commonly grounded upon I know not what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of miſguided conſcience that makes the quarrell the more preſumptuous.</p>
            <p>Other ſinnes, whether of adultery, theft, or drunkenneſſe, dare not appeare in open light: and if they doe, you ſhall find them ready to plead guilty: but the ſinne of ſchiſme that ſpurns men on againſt the orders of the <hi>Church,</hi> is ſo bold and ſawcy of its owne nature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. lib. 3. ep. 9.</hi> Haec ſunt initia haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum, ut ſibi placea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, et Praepoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperbo tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnant. <hi>Pſa. 55. ver. 12. &amp; 13.</hi>
               </note> that it ever ſtands upon juſtification, and being <hi>vainly paſt up with ſelfe-conceit, it dares out-face all authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other ſinnes fight againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, but by way of conſequence; but this fights againſt her with downright blows: and therefore as the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> in a figure of Chriſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains more grievouſly of the plots of his neareſt friends, then of all the treacheries of known foes; ſo the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt his onely Spouſe hath more cauſe to complaine of the civill uncivill wars of her own children, then of all the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of forraigne enemies, that ſeek to bring her into bondage.</p>
            <p>Tis a maxime agreed upon by weeping croſſe that contention goes before deſtruction: there's no State nor Kingdome of the world but have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15930:11"/>made it true by their owne experience: and if the <hi>Church of God</hi> be divided againſt her ſelfe by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry factions, and her children like a rowted diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Army begin to fall upon their own fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, what priviledge have we more then others againſt the generall ſentence of our Saviour. <hi>A Kingdome divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.25</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Optatus</hi> ſaid of the factions of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> that were not much unlike to theſe <hi>contentions,</hi> that <hi>betwixtour yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inter licet noſtrum, &amp; non licet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram nuta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; remiga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nime Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum. Optat. cont. Parmen.</note> 
               <hi>and your nay, the cauſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lyes a bleeding;</hi> and have not we brought it to the ſame paſſe by our domeſticke <hi>quarrells</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, that betwixt the conformity of ſome, and the inconformity of other ſome, many a Chriſtian ſoule ſtands unreſolved, and meanes to continue a meere neutrall.</p>
            <p>As long as <hi>the languages are confounded, the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Church can never goe forward;</hi> as long as the ſhip is toſt with waves, many are afraid to come a ſhipboard, ſome that are without are loth to come in, and ſome that are within are loath to continue; ſo the poore <hi>Church</hi> being ſuſpected and forſaken on both ſides, is faine to complaine with the Prophet <hi>Ieremie: Woe is mee, that ever I was made the cauſe of contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot chuſe but ſee, unleſſe wee wilfully ſhut our eyes,<note place="margin">Auximus Philippu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nos ipſi Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſes.</note> how much our adverſaries are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched by theſe <hi>contentions:</hi> how many good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors upon theſe grounds have leapt aſide into the tents of Popery: how many quier and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able congregations have beene torne and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted into ſundry factions: how many zealous and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15930:11"/>painfull labourers onely for the cauſe of their bare conformity are growne ſuſpected to their owne flockes: and which is moſt to be lamented, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a faithfull and learned Prelate that ſhould be counted worthy of double honour, is traduced as a favourer of Popiſh tyranny, becauſe he labours and ſtrives (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> does here) to beate downe theſe fond and trifling <hi>quarrells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh the day, that ever religion ſhould be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo much irreligion!<note place="margin">Tanium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio potiat ſuadere ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerum?</note> Oh, that the <hi>Church</hi> ſhould ſuffer martyrdome in a heape of vaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary <hi>quarrells!</hi> Have we not <hi>quarrells</hi> enough againſt the Church of Rome for her Purgatory,<note place="margin">Cumque ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perba ſoret Babylon ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianda tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaeis. &amp;c. <hi>Luc:</hi> initio.</note> and Tranſubſtantiation, and prayer for the dead, and invocation of Saints, and adoration of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and pretended infallibility, and many other points of the ſame alloy, but we muſt ſheath our ſwords in our owne bowels, and wilfully invite our owne deſtruction?</p>
            <p>O yee ſonnes of men, how long will you love vanity, how long will you dote upon your owne miſery? Are wee all agreed about the garment, and ſhall we differ about the trimming? are wee agreed about the freehold, and ſhall wee quarrell about the bounds? Away with thoſe unkinde,<note place="margin">Certatum eſt totis &amp;c. in commune nefas. <hi>Philip. 2.</hi>
               </note> unhappy <hi>contentions</hi> that procure the loſſe and ſhame of both ſides, <hi>If there be any joy, if any love, if any compaſsion</hi> either to your ſelves, or to the <hi>Church,</hi> or to the cauſe of reformation, <hi>fulfill my joy,</hi> and the joy of our Apoſtle, and the joy of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the joy of Chriſt Jeſus, and with it the joy of your owne ſoules, that wee may heare
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15930:12"/>no more of theſe fond <hi>contentions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis a ſhame to be ſeene in any quarrell againſt a ceremony,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the bead in praying and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying.</note> yet ſome ceremonies there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt ſo nearely concerning the honour of <hi>God,</hi> that a wilfull and ſtubborne oppoſition cannot chooſe but aggravate and increaſe the fault.</p>
            <p>If ever <hi>contention</hi> againſt a ceremony could threaten to bring us within danger of ſin, I doubt this quarrell in my Text will trench hard upon it, becauſe it trenches ſo neare upon Apoſtolique power.</p>
            <p>The very Apoſtles of Chriſt had a hand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this holy <hi>cuſtome;</hi> for among ſome other orders compoſed by them for the furtherance and decoration of <hi>Gods</hi> ſervice, they ordained this rule for all the <hi>Churches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 2. &amp; 3.</note> 
               <hi>that the men when they came to prayer or prophecie ſhould uncover their heads, and the women ſhould veyle or cover their heads,</hi> as oft as they appear'd in the congregation.<note place="margin">Theophilact. Pet. Mart. &amp; aliiin loc. Gualt in loc. probat hunc Ethnicorum ſuiſſe more<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: idque ex Plutarch. &amp; Virgilio. Jdem Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. graecoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuiſſe inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum: &amp; certum eſt hunc mo. rem hodie apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urcas invaluiſſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That this injunction was in force in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, for ought I find, no man denies: yea ſome there be that give the reaſon of that Canon, that the late converted Chriſtians might not faſhion themſelves to the cuſtomes of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, where the men were <hi>wont to ſacrifice with their heads covered, and the women with their heads bare, and their haire diſheveld, as a greater ſigne and pledge of holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever the reaſon were, I am ſure of this, that the one member at leaſt of that reverend or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I mean that concernes the men, is ſo fully
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15930:12"/>ratifyed and confirmed by the Canon of our <hi>Church, that no man may preſume to cover his head during the whole time of divine Service,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Canon. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> without the breach of <hi>Church</hi> order.</p>
            <p>For the women indeed we have no comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in our <hi>Church,</hi> for nature it ſelf &amp; the rules of modeſty have taught them freely to yeeld con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. But for the men, at leaſt ſome of them in ſome places, where they have beene traind in a courſe of ſchiſme, they are ſo loath to ſtoop to this Apoſtolique order, that the <hi>Church</hi> is fain to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her power to bind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to it by a double bond.</p>
            <p>That any man covers of wilfull ſtubbornneſſe againſt the <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> it were little charity to beleeve: for my part I rather impute it to meere weakneſſe; and could they be throughly reſolved that the reaſon of this <hi>Canon</hi> were yet in force, I preſume there is none of them all of what ſort ſoever, but would thinke themſelves bound to yeeld conformity.</p>
            <p>They think perhaps that this Apoſtolique or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may concern the Miniſters of the <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Objectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt the bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the head, &amp;c Ob. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>it is laid upon fuch as pray and prophecie:</hi> but by their leave, if the hearing of a Sermon be not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying as well as the preaching, and that in the ſenſe and meaning of our own Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note> I deſire to know how the ſame Apoſtle in the next words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately following could apply the ſame words <hi>of praying and propheſying as well to the women as the men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 5.</note> when they were not allowed by his own rule <hi>either to ſpeak or preach in the congregation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.34. &amp; 35. <hi>Ob.</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But ſay it concerne the people as well as the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15930:13"/>Miniſters, as being equally ingaged in praying and propheſying, yet perhaps it may lay a tye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people of thoſe times, and not upon the <hi>Churches</hi> in after ages.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> lib. 4. ca. 20</note> Tis true that all <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of what ſort ſoever, are things diſpenſable in their own nature, yea the very <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of the Apoſtles themſelves are no certaine and perpetuall rules to all <hi>Churches</hi> to abridge their liberty in things indifferent. And what of that? will any man deny them a binding power for the time being while they are allowed by the preſent <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Church</hi> hath power to change when time and place ſhall ſo require? no ſurely, but the ſtampe and impreſſe of the preſent <hi>Church</hi> muſt make them current for the time being: and ſeeing this <hi>cuſtome</hi> is allowed as you heard before, and that under the ſeale of our owne <hi>Church,</hi> let no man preſume to ſtrive againſt it as long as it ſtands ſo allowed, unleſſe he deſire to <hi>ſeeme contentious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps you may ſay, this Apoſtolique <hi>Canon</hi> may not be ſutable to theſe times,<note place="margin">Ob. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> for the Apoſtle ſeems to allow <hi>no covering</hi> at all,<note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note> &amp; if that ſhould be ſtrictly obſerved in this crazie age, we ſhould ſoone make the <hi>Churchyard</hi> full, and the <hi>Church</hi> empty. Well, be it ſo: and what of that? were there not any weak in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time aſwell as now? yes ſurely: why then no doubt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is implyed, though it be not expreſſed in the Text, to ſhew that if we conforme our ſelves as neere as we can, and make uſe <hi>of a coyfe or night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap in ſtead of a hat</hi> (as our Church hath diſpenced with the Apoſtles rule)<note place="margin">Gan. ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> 
               <hi>in caſe of weakneſſe and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15930:13"/>infirmity,</hi> we ſhall never incur the Apoſtles cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor <hi>ſeem to the Church to be contentious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the moſt of our people for ought I ſee are ready to <hi>uncover</hi> in the time of <hi>prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> onely they ſtick at the ſtrictneſſe of ſome that require the <hi>baring of the head</hi> in the time of <hi>preaching:</hi> belike they are willing to ſhew reverence when they ſpeak unto <hi>God</hi> by their earneſt prayers, but they think it too much to ſhew the like when <hi>God</hi> ſpeaks to them by his ſacred ordinance. Let me aſke them, is it not as great a favour to receive a bleſſing, as to crave it? and ſhall we not receive the bleſſing with as much reverence when tis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, as wee would crave it when tis wanting? Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for his part makes no odds <hi>betwixt prayer and propheſie:</hi> and if any man think that the Canon of the <hi>Church</hi> will not reach to both <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it mentions no more but the whole ſervice,</hi> let him pleaſe to compare the words of the Canon to the <hi>rubrick of the ſervice book,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the Nicen Creed.</note> and he ſhall finde <hi>that the Sermon or exhortation</hi> is no other but a part of divine Service.</p>
            <p>There is no diſpenſation for ought I can ſee more for the Sermon then for the prayer:<note place="margin">Ob. <hi>5. Cypr. ep. 73.</hi> Quale. eſt ut quia hoc Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus facere audet, nos putemusnon eſſe ſacien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> neither can I beleeve for mine own part that any man of reaſon or ſound religion would ever ſtick at this reverend order, but that tis the uſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> with which they dare not comply in outward ceremonies, for feare of the danger of ſuperſtition. Indeed tis like enough this Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique order hath been abuſed, and ſcarce can you name any thing elſe that hath not been abuſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15930:14"/>to ſuperſtition, yet when the thing it ſelfe is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon us by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. debap.con. Don lib. 6 cap. 44</hi> Jpſi gentiles ſl quid rectum babuerunt non impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barunt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctipatres, et in hunc mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum lib <hi>3.</hi> ca <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and the ſuperſtition is brought upon it by the fault of men, we muſt not preſume for the fault of men to ſtir a duty of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> preſcribing, but wee muſt learne a better way of reformation, to mend the fault of our owne deviſing, and let the duty ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.</p>
            <p>To be warie of ſuperſtition is a good thing, but there is another extreame to be avoided, which religion hates as well as that: and if we run ſo far from ſuperſtition that wee fall into pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe, and think we have never driven ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition far enough, unleſſe we drive together with it all decent order from the <hi>Churth of God,</hi> I feare we ſhall bring a miſchiefe upon the cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, while wee ſeeke to avoid an inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience.</p>
            <p>Say the Lord hath forbidden ſuperſtition,<note place="margin">Ageneral apologie for the bareing of the head in prayer and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie. <hi>Pſal. 2.11. Heb. 12.28. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> yet I trow he hath commanded <hi>reverence</hi> all along, and <hi>if the baring of the head in the houſe of God during the time of divine ſervice be not a ſigne of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reverence,</hi> I am yet to learne what reverence meanes.</p>
            <p>Sure we make it a ſigne of reverence in civill worſhip, for ſervants uncover to their maſters, children to their parents, ſubjects to their prince, yea and to the chaire of his ſtate to, as a type and figure of his preſence: and will you refuſe to give the ſame reverence in divine worſhip to the great King of all the earth, when he claimes it of you by the ſame titles of reſpect,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>If I be a father,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15930:14"/>where is my honour; if I be a Lord, where is my reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will not come into the court of a Prince as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> notes, but you will <hi>compoſe your ſelves in gate, and eye, and habit, and geſture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom. 24. in Act. &amp; 36. in 1. Cor. Idem Martyr, in loc. &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſm. de morum ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo in huc modum:</hi> Si quis regem hominem alloquutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum corona nec caput a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periat, nec genu flectat, non iam pro ruſtico ſed pro inſano haberetur.</note> leaſt you may offend in any reſpect, and will yee come into the pallace of the great King with wandring eyes, and mincing feet, and heads covered, as if you made no more of the houſe of God, <hi>then of a taverne or barbars ſhop?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I heare good <hi>Iacob</hi> crying out when the Lord appeared to him by the way to Haran:<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 28.19, 20. Lev. 19 30 Exod. 30.18.</note> 
               <hi>Surely the Lord is in this place, and I was not aware; how feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and terrible is this place, this is no other but the houſe of God, and the gate of heaven:</hi> and canſt not thou behold the preſence of God in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and congregations of his Saints, when thou ſpeakeſt to him by thy zealous prayers, or hee to thee by his ſacred word?</p>
            <p>I heare the Lord charging the Jewes, that they ſhould <hi>reverence his very Sanctuary,</hi> as being the place where the Lord appeared; and ſhall not we reverence his word, and his ſacraments, and his oracles, and his ordinances, when we appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in his holy Sanctuary?</p>
            <p>Did the wiſe King give it in charge, <hi>that wee ſhould looke to our feet when we enter into Gods houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 4.17.</note> and is there no regard to be had to our heads?<note place="margin">Exod. 3.5.</note> Was <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded <hi>to put off his ſhoes when he appeared before the Lord,</hi> and doe we thinke much to put off our hatts?<note place="margin">1 Sam. 5.5.</note> Did the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> give ſo much <hi>unto Dagon,</hi> and the <hi>Syrians</hi> ſo much to their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15930:15"/>god <hi>Rimmon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 5.18.</note> and cannot wee afford as much as they, to the great Creator of heaven and earth?</p>
            <p>Let me aſke the queſtion with divine <hi>Salvian,</hi> Wherefore do ye come to the houſe of God,<note place="margin">Anides ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimu ad placandum ſimul et ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acerbandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. anejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcere &amp; ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundiam provocare?</note> if you ſhew no more regard to his holy ordinances? <hi>Doe ye come to pacifie and aſſwage his wrath, and doe yee kindle and provoke his wrath? Is it the ſame work both to honour God, and diſhonour him too? To ſue for his favour, and ſet a barre againſt his favour?</hi> Wilt thou preſume to offer unto God that ſurly <hi>ſervice,</hi> which thou wouldſt take in ſcorne from thine owne ſervant? Muſt God take that for an honour to himſelfe, which thou thy ſelfe wouldſt take for a foule diſhonour? Muſt he account it a pacification, which thou thy ſelfe wouldſt take for a provocation? Away with ſuch a proud and ſawcy ſubmiſſion, away with ſuch a rude, unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly ſervice; Let us never be guilty of ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour unto God,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>4</hi> ſupr:</note> 
               <hi>Let us never bee guilty of ſuch diſhonour to our ſelves:</hi> If we ſtand not ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our owne honour, yet take heed how wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the honour of God; if we feare not ſo much the cenſure of men,<note place="margin">Sigenus humanum &amp; mortalia temaitis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, at ſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Deum. &amp;c.</note> yet take heed <hi>how we fall into the hands of God:</hi> Let it never be ſaid of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, that the heathens worſhip their owne handy works with more reverence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, then we adore the maker of all things: let it never be laid to the reformed <hi>Churches,</hi> that <hi>wee have choſen to our ſelves an eaſie and ſlovenly kinde of ſervice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stapleton orat. quodl:</note> 
               <hi>to the ſhame and diſhonour of religion:</hi> If o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Churches</hi> are guilty of that fault, oh let not us ſuffer for their offence; if any of our peeviſh bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15930:15"/>have offended, oh let not our mother beare the blame. Shee hath done what ſhe can for the honour and reverence of her huſband, for ſhee hath made a <hi>law</hi> to binde her children, ſhee hath practiſed that <hi>law</hi> in the godly examples of her <hi>governours,</hi> ſhe hath cenſured the breach of it in ſome of her ſtubborne and rebellious children; and if all this be not enough to perſwade reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, what can ſhe doe more, but give them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the juſt cenſure of her huſband, who will ſurely prove a ſharpe avenger upon the heads <hi>of thoſe that love contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſeene the ground of this vaine <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> together with the time it began to hatch;<note place="margin">By who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was ſet a foote.</note> and now could we ſearch a little further, and find out the author of this <hi>quarrell,</hi> we might do a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious worke to the <hi>Church</hi> of God, to draw the pedigree of <hi>Contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſome notorious ſchiſmatique began this quarrell, we may eaſily judge by S. <hi>Pauls</hi> (<hi>Si quis</hi>) no famous ſchiſme ever began without ſome head and ringleader of the faction, yet becauſe the head of this trifling faction, may ſeem to be a man of unworthy parts, as moſt of that brood have ever beene, the Apoſtle would not vouchſafe to give him a name, for feare he ſhould give him too much honour.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>All the title he gives him here is (<hi>contentioſus, a contentious man,</hi>) to teach us that whoſoever ſtrives againſt the orders of the <hi>Church,</hi> ſpecially thoſe that tend to reverence, hee may enjoy the name of a <hi>contentious man,</hi> and muſt not look for a better title.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15930:16"/>
Whatſoever may be thought of other cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, yet. I am ſure this quarrell in my text will beare the title;<note place="margin">Vide ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. 18. ut ſupr:</note> for when the <hi>Church allowes a coife or nightcay in caſe of weakneſſe and infirmity,</hi> and men, ſhall wilfully refuſe to enjoy that favour, to pick a quarrell with the <hi>Church of God;</hi> what Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate will undertake to plead their cauſe that they may not ſtand upon record <hi>for contentious men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould be loath to ſay that the bare omiſſion of this order, or any other ſhould conclude a man to be <hi>contentious;</hi> Nay, S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe doth not goe ſo farre, till he had ſhewed the ground of this holy order: but if any ſhall wilfully oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves after lawfull warning and inſtruction, then we have our warrant from the bleſſed Apoſtle to write them downe <hi>for contentious men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To ſeeme contentious</hi> is a ſmall matter, but S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe goes a great deale further, and ſets him downe to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, a <hi>lover of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> as if he loved <hi>contention</hi> as he loved his life, and doted upon it as the wanton dotes upon his miſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>We know it is one thing <hi>to fall into contention,</hi> and another thing <hi>to fall in love with contention it ſelfe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 120.5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> himſelfe may fall into <hi>contention</hi> and ſinga [<hi>Vae</hi>] to himſelfe, when he cannot avoid it, but to be enamored and beſotted <hi>with the love of contention</hi> is ſuch a fearefull ſickneſſe, and frenzie of the ſoule, that it ſeemes to be paſt all hope of cure.<note place="margin">Pro. 17.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where this love of contention is, there is much tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15930:16"/>Nay there is a whole ſwarme of ugly vices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>there is envy, there is pride, there is tumult, there is malice, there is revenge, there is murther, there is ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is treaſon, there is ſchiſme, there is hereſie,</hi> there is all things; as if all the maladies of the ſoul were epitomized and ſummed up in this word, (<hi>contentious</hi>)</p>
            <p>Take but a view of this one <hi>contention</hi> in my text, and ſee what bordering miſchiefe hangs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: the Apoſtle is ſo well acquainted with all the neighborhood,<note place="margin">The love of conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tends to ſchiſme and that ſeldome ends till it comes to hereſy.</note> that in the compaſſe of two<note n="*" place="margin">Viz. 18, &amp; 19.</note> verſes he makes it ſhake hands with <hi>ſchiſme</hi> and <hi>hereſie,</hi> as if they both tooke head from the <hi>love of contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps the neighborhood of ſchiſme will hardly ſtagger us, for many thinke it a title of honour, and when they ſuffer in that cauſe, they thinke they <hi>ſuffer as a Chriſtian:</hi> but S. <hi>Paul</hi> that was better acquainted with the nature of ſchiſme, is bold to rank it with the fouleſt ſinnes that can be named, <hi>Adultery, Murther, Idolatry, Witchcraft,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.19. &amp; 20. Lib. 2. de bapt. cont. Donat. ca. 6. Idem Optat. 1. lib. contr: Parmen: <hi>Quis dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet celerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum quod gravius pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and ſuch like;</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will tell us, if wee can beleeve him, that when it is put on with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full violence, and maintained with heat of phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall pride, it proves no leſſer ſinne in the ſight of God, then either <hi>Adultery, Theft, or Murther,</hi> and hath beene commonly revenged with greater puniſhments.</p>
            <p>If you are not ſtirred with the danger of <hi>ſchiſm</hi> that borders ſo neare upon the <hi>love of contention;</hi> what doe you thinke of the nature of <hi>hereſie</hi> that is commonly entailed to the ſin of <hi>ſchiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15930:17"/>
Surely the Apoſtle had never coupled <hi>hereſies</hi> and <hi>ſchiſmes</hi> both together, but that he knew well enough that <hi>ſchiſme</hi> is nothing elſe but a greene <hi>hereſie</hi> newly hatcht in the <hi>Church</hi> of God, and <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> nothing elſe, but a growne <hi>ſchiſme</hi> that is come to ripeneſſe and perfection.</p>
            <p>There is neither of them both but ſpring from the ſame fountaine, for <hi>contention</hi> is the head of both the factions, and as it ſpurs on the one with earneſt violence againſt <hi>the diſcipline of the Church;</hi> ſo it eggs on the other with headſtrong fury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>the doctrine of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though every <hi>contentious man</hi> bee neither a <hi>ſchiſmatick,</hi> nor an <hi>heretick,</hi> yet he hath a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to be made both, he runnes ſo fierce upon a full carere of headſtrong paſſion, like a man that gallops downe a hill, that hee can hardly take up and ſtay his pace untill he come to the bottome of <hi>hereſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man becomes an <hi>hereticke</hi> on a ſuddaine, but windes into it by certaine ſteps; and loe the ſtaires are ſet by the bleſſed Apoſtle: <hi>Firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> in this verſe; <hi>then ſchiſme in the</hi> 18. then <hi>hereſie in the</hi> 19. to teach us that if we deſire to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void <hi>hereſie,</hi> we muſt firſt begin to cut off <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> and if we deſire to flye the danger of <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> wee muſt firſt begin to ſtrike at <hi>contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>waters of contention muſt be ſtopped in the firſt breach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17.14</note> that they may not turne to an inundation.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Bab loniſh brats muſt be daſhed againſt the walls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.9</note> that they may not grow to further miſchief.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Cockatrices egge muſt be cracked in the ſhell,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15930:17"/>that it may not bring forth a flying ſerpent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh who will <hi>take theſe foxes, theſe young foxes in the neaſt, that they may not infeſt the tender grapes!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 2.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Oh who will quench theſe coales of diſſention, that they may not increaſe to a greater flame.</p>
            <p>Stand to your tackle O yee Champions of the Lord, and let not the enemy get ground upon you: <hi>If it be poſsible,</hi> as much as in you lies <hi>have peace with all men:</hi> If diſcord ariſe betwixt man and man, let it never incroach upon Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Behold how good and joyfull it is brethren to live together in unity:</hi> O bleſſed Peace, wee are all thy clyents; nothing can comfort us without thy company, <hi>Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 122.6, 7</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall proſper that love thee, peace bee within thy walls, and plenteouſneſſe within thy pallaces: for my brethren and companions ſake, I cannot chuſe but wiſh thy peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let every one beſtirre himſelfe in the Lords worke, as it were in a time of common danger; one to ſpeake for <hi>peace,</hi> another to labour for <hi>peace,</hi> another to fight for <hi>peace,</hi> another to pray for <hi>peace,</hi> that ſo by the bleſſing of God upon our joynt endeavours, we may live to ſee the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py greeting and ſalutation of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10</note> to the joy and comfort of all our hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercy and truth ſhall meet together, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and peace have kiſſed each other. Truth ſhall bud ont of the earth, and righteouſneſſe ſhall look downe from heaven: The Lord ſhall ſhew his loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and our land ſhall give her increaſe: Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall goe before him, and he ſhall direct our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo be it: Lord ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15930:18"/>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15930:18"/>
            <head>CHVRCH-CVSTOMES VINDICATED.</head>
            <head type="sub">The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 11.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If any man luſt to bee contentious, Wee have no ſuch Cuſtome, nor the Churches of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this very place upon the like occaſion about five years ſince, we made an entrance upon this theame, and being now preſſed againe upon the ſame ſervice, I thought my ſelfe directed and led by the hand to the further explanation of the ſame Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that as I ſpake before you at that time of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15930:19"/>the <hi>contentions. of the Church</hi> that let themſelves againſt the <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> ſo now I may ſpeak before you of the <hi>Churches cuſtomes,</hi> that ſtrenuouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt <hi>contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What I then delivered concerning <hi>contention,</hi> I will not call to your mind againe, I deſire that <hi>cuſtome being defendant</hi> may have a fair and legall hearing, as well as <hi>contention</hi> that was the <hi>plaintife</hi> in the cauſe.</p>
            <p>Whether any ſuch ſpirits live amongſt us that deſerve the title of <hi>contentious,</hi> I could not ſay, nor yet can: for my part I confeſſe I know of none, neither doe I ſpeak to gall any, I did but onely put a caſe as S. <hi>Paul</hi> does,<note place="margin">Conditiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis propoſitio nihil ponit in eſſe.</note> (and a meere ſuppoſition inferrs nothing) but if any be, or hereafter may be, though it be more then appeares to me, yet you may know by the caſe put, how to file their teeth, and muzzle their mouthes, that they may not infeſt the flock of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>If you know of any <hi>contentious men</hi> what ever they be,<note place="margin">How wee may deal with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious men.</note> that live like the Salamander in the fire, and love to wrangle &amp; ſpend their breath againſt the decent orders and conſtitutions of the <hi>Church,</hi> you were beſt to aſke of the bleſſed Apoſtle, and he will teach you how to handle them.</p>
            <p>You muſt be ſure to uſe all gentle meanes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you come to ſharpneſſe and ſeverity: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will lead, that will not drive, and yeeld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a gentle entreaty, that will not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by compulſion.</p>
            <p>You ſhall do well in the firſt place to ſet before them your own example,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for ſo the Apoſtle doth in the 1. ver.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15930:19"/>
You may take occaſion to commend them for their zeale and ſtrictneſſe in ſome thing elſe; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for ſo the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath taught you, ver. 2.</p>
            <p>You muſt not faile to inſtruct them in the meaning and ſignification of the ceremonies,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for ſo the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> taught you, ver. 3.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay? you may perſwade them by <hi>reaſon,</hi> by <hi>authority,</hi> by <hi>decency,</hi> by <hi>nature</hi> it ſelfe, for none of theſe hath Saint <hi>Paul</hi> omitted, and if all this be not able to perſwade (for who can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a <hi>contentious man,</hi> you ſhall not perſwade though you doe perſwade, not perſwade his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice I meane, though you perſwade and convict his conſcience) then you muſt beare him downe with the <hi>Churches cuſtome,</hi> and tell him plainly to his face that the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> muſt ſtand in force maugre the ſpight of <hi>contentious men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The power of <hi>cuſtome</hi> no doubt is great, and that of the <hi>Church</hi> not leaſt of all, but leſt I may be thought to preſſe the <hi>cuſtome</hi> before I have taught you to underſtand the <hi>cuſtome,</hi> you ſhall give mee leave to ſpeak ſomething concerning the <hi>theorie</hi> of the <hi>cuſtome,</hi> that ſo I may riſe with the more force to the <hi>practice</hi> and <hi>obſervation</hi> of the <hi>cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While I entreat of <hi>Church order,</hi> me thinks I am bound to keep order, and becauſe the nature of the ſubject will ſcarce afford any quaint order, I will content my ſelfe with a plaine method.</p>
            <p>Three things there be that offer themſelves.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>uſe</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>having</hi> of <hi>cuſtomes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15930:20"/>
2. The <hi>right</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in making of <hi>cuſtomes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in preſſing of <hi>cuſtomes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the <hi>cuſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cuſtome what it is</note> firſt, to underſtand that through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you muſt pleaſe to look back to the 2. ver. there the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> mentions ſome <hi>ordinances</hi> or <hi>traditions</hi> which he had <hi>delivered</hi> to the <hi>Church of Corinth:</hi> 2. there he commends their zealous care, becauſe they had kept the moſt of them. 3. and then he condemns their halting obedience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had failed in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p>What thoſe <hi>ordinances</hi> were is all the matter that concerns us, and becauſe there is mention made of one or two, and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of them, wee muſt judge of the Lion by his paw, and gueſſe that the reſt were all of the ſame ſtamp, being all commended at one time to one and the ſelfe ſame <hi>Church of Corinth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> meant by his <hi>ordinances,</hi> ver. 2. and by his <hi>orders,</hi> ver. ult. the ſame he meanes by his <hi>cuſtomes</hi> here: all <hi>matters of rite and outward ceremony annexed to the preaching of the Word and adminiſtration of the Sacraments, not as parts of Gods holy worſhip, but as appendices thereunto onely for the order of Gods houſe, and diſpoſition of his ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such were the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Such cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> and ſuch <hi>cuſtomes</hi> as theſe were about <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> and <hi>outward geſture,</hi> whether it be <hi>kneeling, ſtanding, bowing, croſsing, uncovering,</hi> or whatſoever elſe of the ſame alloy, as they were freely uſed in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſo they muſt needs be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15930:20"/>allowed in every age in all the <hi>aſſemblies</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſhall never heare of any <hi>famous Church</hi> ſince the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time that hath not freely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed ſome <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of this kind; and you ſhall never reade of any learned <hi>orthodox father</hi> ſince the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time that ever oppugned the uſe of theſe <hi>cuſtomes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In the primitive Church.</hi> Auguſt. ep. 118. ad Ian. Amb. in 4. Epheſ. Socra. hiſt. li. 5. ca. 22. z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zomen. li. 7. ca. 9. Tertul. de veland. vir.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I could eaſily ſhew you upon good authority that all the <hi>ancient Churches</hi> had their ſeverall <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> and that while they enjoyed the ſame faith, and which is more to be obſerved and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, the <hi>difference and contrarietie of their cuſtoms did neither diſſolve the bond of charity, nor diſturb the unity of religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtolique Churches</hi> had their <hi>cuſtomes</hi> to, yea, for ought we know, ſeverall <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> yet all by Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> free allowance:<note place="margin">In the Apoſt. churches.</note> for though hee ſtover a little as good cauſe he had againſt a new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangled <hi>cuſtome</hi> of their own deviſing, which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious men</hi> would faine keep up, yet withall hee ſeemes to imply <hi>by way of conceſsion,</hi> that they had ſome <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of another kind, which he would not ſuffer to be borne downe, by the heat of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full oppoſition.</p>
            <p>Thoſe <hi>cuſtomes</hi> what ever they were, were not onely allowed to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In all the Apoſt. churches.</note> but to all the <hi>Churches</hi> of that time, or at leaſt to many of them; for the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth not ſpeak in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar number, as of <hi>one Church,</hi> but in the plurall number, as of <hi>many.</hi> And if the <hi>Churches</hi> in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt times had all their <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> and thoſe in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15930:21"/>
               <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time their <hi>cuſtomes</hi> to, I wonder why the <hi>Churches</hi> in theſe times, and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> among the reſt, the gracious Mother of us all, may not bee quietly ſuffered to enjoy her <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were the <hi>ceremonies</hi> and <hi>orders of the church</hi> an ornament to <hi>religion</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> dayes, and are they now become in theſe latter times a ſtain and blemiſh to <hi>religion?</hi> had the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>God</hi> their earerings, their bracelets, and their jewels in the nonage and childhood of <hi>religion,</hi> and muſt they now be ſtript of all in the growth and ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>goſpell?</hi> Alas <hi>poore mother,</hi> what haſt thou done to be ſo ſhamefully uſed of thine own <hi>children?</hi> alas <hi>good children,</hi> what doe you meane to offer ſuch wrong to your deare mother? Did <hi>David</hi> bring a ſcorne upon his perſon when hee <hi>uncovered</hi> himſelfe before his ſubjects,<note place="margin">zSam. 6.20</note> and would not you bring a ſcorne upon your <hi>mother</hi> if you ſhould uncover her ſhame before all her <hi>children?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſutarch. Cat. Vtic.</note> Did <hi>Cato Vtican</hi> draw a ſcorne upon his juſtice when hee went to his <hi>pretorian ſeat</hi> without his robes, and may not we bring the like upon <hi>Gods ſervice,</hi> if we ſhould repaire to the ſeat of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>common garments?</hi> I beſeech you for the honour of God, for the honour of religion for the honour of your ſelves, think upon your bold and raſh ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures: it is not the <hi>cuſtome</hi> ſhe regards ſo much as your obedience to the <hi>cuſtome:</hi> and if you be ſo ſtiffe and cruell to your <hi>mother,</hi> that ſhe may not enjoy her <hi>ancient cuſtomes,</hi> why ſhould ſhe allow your <hi>ancient diſcipline</hi> (as you call it) which you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15930:21"/>can never demand upon better warrant? You ſay the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had the <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> but we are ſure of this, they had the <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> and if you ſeeke to rob us of thoſe rites which we know the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> once delivered, why ſhould we give way to your new pretended forme of <hi>Geneva diſcipline,</hi> which I doubt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> never heard of? Shew us that warrant for your <hi>diſcipline,</hi> as wee have ſhewed you for our <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> and wee ſhall have cauſe to hearken to you: In the meane while wee have right enough to enjoy our <hi>ceremonies</hi> by the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> leave if not by yours; and though you thinke it a ragge of Rome, and a relique of Popery and ſuperſtition; yet we ſhall rejoyce and triumph at all your taunts, as long as we can ſay with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Apoſtle, habemus conſuetudinem, wee have a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To have a <hi>cuſtome</hi> is not much,<note place="margin">Right of the Chu: in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cuſtomes</note> but all the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is by what pretended right wee hold the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man heares of the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> for the ordering and diſpoſing of Gods ſervice, but preſently he begins to examine our Patent, and to renew the queſtion of thoſe Prieſts and Elders, <hi>Qua poteſtate?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.23</note> 
               <hi>By what authoritie doe you theſe things, and who gave you that authority?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Church</hi> I trow will doe nothing without a warrant, and if ſhee have that warrant from her huſband, bequeathed unto her in his Teſtament, reade us the Will and it ſufficeth; But if ſhee take her power from the <hi>will of man,</hi> or from the <hi>favour of Princes,</hi> or from the <hi>authoritie of her governours;</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15930:22"/>then you muſt give us leave to put in a caveat, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be tryed by the <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Loe this is the plea of all the ſectaries in the world,<note place="margin">Nulla ſpecie illuſtriore ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>duci poſ ſunt miſeri Chriſtians, &amp;c. <hi>Calv. adver. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabapt.</hi>
               </note> [Shew us your ceremonies in the word of God and we ſhall be willing to obey] and it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes the more with many a man, becauſe it ſeemes to give to the written word: but if it appeare upon juſt tryall that the word of God (with honour and reverence be it ſpoken) was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſtituted as the judge for the ſpeciall deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of particular ceremonies; then wee come upon them,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.22</note> 
               <hi>like the ſtrong man armed in the Goſpell, that take away their weapons wherein they truſt, and liave them nothing to object.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whileſt I take upon me to make this good,<note place="margin">Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes depend not upon the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe warrant of the word.</note> let no man thinke I diſhonour the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> let ſhame and confuſion fall to my portion, if I caſt any blurre upon that ſacred volume: I know well that it is the priviledge of the <hi>Scripture</hi> to bee the onely <hi>rule of faith and manners,</hi> and it was the only ſcope of the holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 20.30</note> 
               <hi>to leave a perfect record of all thoſe things that might eſſentially conduce to our ſalvation:</hi> For other <hi>accidentall adventitious</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that were no part of the ſervice of God, but onely an ornament to the ſervice, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not good to the Spirit of God that they ſhould paſſe by the ſame Patent.</p>
            <p>Well may they paſſe in generall tearmes (as many things are conveyed in every deed under the name of the appurtenances) but they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver expreſſed in that gracious Patent by any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall intimation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:15930:22"/>
Well may they belong to thoſe <hi>traditions which the Apoſtle delivered by word of mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>but they can be no part of that holy tradition which he delivered to the Church by his written Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well may you referre them to thoſe <hi>rituall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> which our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> promiſed to compoſe when he came to <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. ult.</note> but you cannot referre them to that heavenly doctrine of which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayes a little before; <hi>Accepi à Domina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 23.</note> 
               <hi>I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, all that I can finde in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament concerning ceremonies, is nothing elſe but a generall warrant, that you have in expreſſe tearmes: 1 <hi>Car.</hi> 14.40.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> 
               <hi>That all things bee done de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently, and According to order;</hi> but for the ſpeciall <hi>practiſie</hi> and <hi>application</hi> of <hi>this order;</hi> whether this or that be more agreeable to the rule, there the word is ſo mute and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lent, that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> finde the leaſt title.</p>
            <p>No doubt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> compoſed ſome <hi>ſpeciall orders:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calvin. Theophil. &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> compoſed the <hi>Churches obſerved</hi> what he delivered; and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe can bee found in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Scriptures, why ſhould we look for a <hi>ſpeciall warrant</hi> for the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſpoſition of things indifferent.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Churches</hi> were bound to thoſe ſtrait conditions,<note place="margin">The Church is not ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to any. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in matter of cuſtome.</note> there is none of them all for ought I can ſee, but have forfeited their recogniſance long agoe, in aſmuch as they have uſed ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>cuſtomes</hi> which were not <hi>expreſſed</hi> in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15930:23"/>
               <hi>Cartwright</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">Pag. 22. ſect. 1. &amp; 2. apud Dr. Whitgift anſwer to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, &amp;c.</note> the great ſcourge of all our <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> while hee ſeekes to binde us to the ſpeciall <hi>warrant</hi> of the word for all particulars, is forced to confeſſe for the <hi>Iewiſh Church,</hi> that ſhee had <hi>many and ſundry cuſtomes, at leaſt twenty for our one,</hi> about <hi>ſacrificing,</hi> and <hi>preaching,</hi> and <hi>burying,</hi> and <hi>marrying,</hi> and <hi>faſting, &amp;c.</hi> which were no where expreſſed in the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. S. Baſ. ep 63. Cypr: l. 10. ep. 12. &amp; l. 4 ep. 6. Epiſt. ad Vict. Rom apud E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſeb. l. 5. cap. 25. &amp; 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the Chriſtian <hi>Church</hi> had the ſame liberty no man can doubt that hath read any thing; for beſide the records of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who give us ſome hints of ſundry <hi>cuſtomes about prayer, and baptiſme, and ſinging of Pſalmes, and celebration of Eaſter,</hi> which I could never finde in the word of God:<note n="*" place="margin">Adver. Praxeam &amp; lib. de corona militis.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> for his part is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and peremptory upon his own knowledge, that for matter of rite and outward order, <hi>Si le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem expoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es ſcriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>venies nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>am: If you looke for the Law of the word of God, you ſhall be ſure to finde none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſhew this liberty of the <hi>Church</hi> in ſome particulars.<note place="margin">Vid. Hila. praefat. in Pſ. Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. adverſ. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer. Juſt. Mart. lib. quaeſt. idem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmat. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. can 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Where can you finde in the holy Scriptures that we ought to pray ſtanding on the Lords day? yet that was the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of the ancients for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſeaſon, to preſerve the memory of the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where can you ſhew in the word of God that we ought to communicate every day? yet that was the <hi>uſe</hi> in the <hi>ancient Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. ep ad Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. &amp; Aug. ep. ad Caſula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> to keep the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the paſſion.</p>
            <p>Where doe you reade in the word of God that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15930:23"/>you ought to receive the Communion faſting? yet that was the univerſal <hi>cuſtom</hi> of all the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Saint Auguſtines time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 118. ad Ianuar.</note> to preſerve the honour of the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be ſhort, if you think the letter of the word be ſo requiſite to every <hi>cuſtome,</hi> you were beſt to ſurvey the writings of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and ſee what order you can find for <hi>ſtanding holydayes:</hi> what ſpeciall warrant for ſet <hi>faſts</hi> upon <hi>certaine dayes:</hi> what expreſſe charge to keep the firſt day of <hi>the week for the Chriſtian Sabbath:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ca. 20. &amp; Epiſc. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> tract. de Sab. pap. 98.</note> what expreſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate warrant to chriſten or <hi>baptize a young In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant:</hi> I doubt you will find no more but a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall warrant for any of theſe, though they have been conſtantly obſerved in all ages: and if every of theſe have been held by <hi>cuſtome,</hi> being onely grounded upon the generall warrant of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and deduced from thence by good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence without any ſpeciall intimation, why ſhould we be tyed to a <hi>ſpeciall order</hi> for the ruling and diſpoſing of every ceremony?</p>
            <p>If the <hi>ſpeciall warrant</hi> of the Word be ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, you were beſt to blame the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of Chriſt,<note place="margin">The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles never compoſed any ſet forme of outward rite. <hi>Inſtit. li. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. 10. ſect. 30.</hi>
               </note> becauſe they forgot to entreat of <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> rites: and if a <hi>generall warrant</hi> be not ſufficient, you were beſt to blame the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they took too much upon them.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> firſt, you cannot blame them; for <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelfe can tell you that they had no commiſſion from the Lord to ſet downe a forme of outward diſcipline; <hi>inaſmuch</hi> as he foreſaw <hi>how that depended upon the ſtate of the times, neither
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15930:24"/>could he judge any one forme to be agreeable to all people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He knew well enough that the <hi>Church</hi> was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to <hi>waxes</hi> and <hi>wanes,</hi> to <hi>fulls</hi> and <hi>changes,</hi> and <hi>viciſsitudes;</hi> and therefore as a rare and cunning workman can hardly make a garment for the moone, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> notes, that ſhould equally fit her at all ſeaſons, as well in the new as in the full, no more could the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> judge any one form of <hi>unchangeable cuſtome</hi> to be agreeable to all times and the various conditions of all people.<note place="margin">All parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars in this kind depend upon the authority of the Church.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But then perhaps you will blame the <hi>Church</hi> becauſe ſhe preſumes to run of her ſelfe without a ſpeciall commiſſion for every <hi>cuſtome:</hi> No ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but where the Word of <hi>God</hi> is dumbe and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, there the voice of the <hi>Church</hi> muſt be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: In this caſe the very ſilence of the word gives conſent that the cauſe belongs to another court: and ſeeing the word is ſilent concerning <hi>ceremonies,</hi> and ſpeaks nothing of them in explicite termes, where may we looke for a certaine <hi>dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and <hi>reſolution</hi> in that caſe, but from the <hi>power of the Church,</hi> and from the <hi>authority of her paſtors?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep. ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulanum,</hi> In quibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> certi ſtatuit ſcript. m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s populi Dei &amp; inſtituta majorum pro lege te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda ſunt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being aſked his opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a <hi>cuſtome</hi> uſed in his time, takes occaſion to anſwer in briefe, not onely for that, but for all others of the ſame ſtamp, that <hi>where the Word of God determines no certainty, there the cuſtome of the Church, and the conſtitutions of her Paſtors are to be taken for a law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this was the generall judgement of all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15930:24"/>the <hi>Churches</hi> in all ages, if any man doubt, let him reade the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Councels:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beza. lib. conf. fidei Chri. ca. 5.</note> for why ſhould the <hi>Councels</hi> be called together to order the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>Church,</hi> and to ſettle the forme of outward diſcipline, but that they held it a maxime in all ages, that the <hi>Church had power of things indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Divine of our owne ſide of any note that ſtick at this power,<note place="margin">Beza. conf. fidei. Gualt. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. in 2. Cor. Zuin. li. de bapt. Chem. loc. com. tit. tradit. Mar. in 1 Cor. 1. Calv. com. in loc.</note> ſo it goe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for beſides the judgement of <hi>Beza, Bucer, Zuinglius, Chemnitius, Peter Martyr,</hi> and generally all the Worthies of theſe latter times that freely allow it with one conſent, you ſhall take the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Calvin,</hi> one for all, who ſets it down for a certaine rule upon the light he drew from this preſent Cap. that every <hi>Church of what place ſoever may ſafely compoſe ſuch a forme of diſcipline, as may be moſt agreeable to it ſelfe, becauſe the Lord therein hath preſcribed no certainty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelfe is ſo cleare in this, that no man can make any further doubt: for when he ſeeks to ſuppreſſe an upſtart <hi>cuſtome</hi> by a <hi>(non habemus talem,)</hi> and grounds himſelfe upon this reaſon, becauſe <hi>they nor the Churches had none ſuch,</hi> what doth he but inferre by way of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that the practice of the <hi>Church; and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of her Paſtors, is warrant enough for any ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It makes me wonder the more, and who doth not wonder at the froward humour of ſome pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Noveliſts, that think all the <hi>practice of the Church in things indifferent,</hi> to be nothing elſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15930:25"/>but <hi>uſurpation,</hi> and all <hi>her decent and reverend cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> that ſerve for the furtherance of GODs ſervice to bee nothing elſe but a meere <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their ſpight is ſo great againſt the preſent go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, becauſe it croſſes their ſelfe-will'd hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, that they will ſcarce allow that power to the <hi>Church</hi> in the meaneſt things, that every Church-warden and meane Artificer would ſoon challenge, if they might be left to their owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>Belike the <hi>Seers of the Lord are become blind,</hi> that they cannot diſcerne the meaneſt things; or elſe the <hi>ſtewards of the Lord are become unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> that they may not be truſted with the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ceremony.</p>
            <p>But well fare the good and courteous <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan;</hi> he was not halfe ſo ſtrait to the good <hi>Inkeeper</hi> when he gave him the care of the <hi>wounded tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller</hi> in the Goſpell, ſo willing was he to enlarge his favour, that beſide the <hi>two pence</hi> hee left to diſcharge the reckoning, hee gave him leave <hi>to ſpend more, and to runne upon the ſcore till his next returne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Aug. de quaeſt. Euang. li. 2. quaeſt. 59. Ambro. &amp; Origen. in Luc. Maca. Cyrill. &amp; alios in Cat. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. patrum in Luc.</note>
            </p>
            <p>No doubt a large allowance given to a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but if we be the <hi>wounded travellers, as indeed we are,</hi> that unhappily miſcarried in <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, and if the two pence he left us to diſcharge the <hi>reckoning</hi> may ſeeme to allude, as moſt expound it, to the <hi>two Tables</hi> of <hi>the Teſtament,</hi> I wonder what courſe we may take to ſpend the <hi>overplus</hi> that he may <hi>allow it at his comming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15930:25"/>
In neceſſary expences for food or phyſick wee need not <hi>ſpend above our two pence:</hi> in points of <hi>faith</hi> and works of <hi>ſupererrogation, we muſt not ſpend</hi> above our allowance: perhaps we may <hi>ſpend</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more to advance the honour of the good <hi>Samaritan:</hi> and if we ſpend the <hi>overplus in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> for the furtherance and advancement of his ſervice, I make no doubt when <hi>he comes againe to take the account of all our expences,</hi> he will not ſtick to allow the <hi>overplus,</hi> with an <hi>ego reddam, I will pay it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they may chance to ſay,<note place="margin">Ob. <hi>Con. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dér. decret. 1. Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.</hi> Paripietatis affectu tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiones una cum libris veteris &amp; novi Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus.</note> this faire allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance given to the <hi>Church,</hi> may make too much for the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> that makes <hi>the voice of the Church, the voice of God, and equalls the power of her owne traditions with the peereleſſe authority of the written word.</hi> And what if ſome offend in exceſſe and laviſhneſſe, muſt we therefore offend in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and want? what if they give the <hi>Church</hi> too much, muſt we give too little or nothing at all? what if they ſtraine the power <hi>of the Church,</hi> even to points of <hi>doctrine,</hi> and <hi>articles of faith,</hi> ſhall wee abridge and ſcant <hi>her power,</hi> that ſhee may not reach to points of <hi>diſcipline?</hi> Nay rather let the <hi>Scripture</hi> enjoy her right in matter of <hi>faith,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> her <hi>intereſt</hi> in <hi>matter of cuſtome:</hi> that's a priviledge given to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> this a <hi>permiſsion</hi> left unto the <hi>Church: He that is Lord of all, may doe what he will with his owne goods,</hi> whether hee give more or leſſe to the ſacred Scripture, <hi>what is it to thee, Sume quod tuum eſt, &amp; vade. O Church, take thine owne, and go thy way,</hi> thou haſt power enough
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15930:26"/>to uſe a <hi>ceremony,</hi> thou haſt power enough to make a <hi>ceremony;</hi> let us now proceed a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſee what power thou haſt to preſſe a <hi>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The making of a <hi>ceremony</hi> is not much,<note place="margin">How the Church may urge her cuſt:</note> and the uſe of a <hi>ceremony</hi> leaſt of all; all the matter is about the urging of a <hi>ceremony,</hi> that may chance to urge a many of us.</p>
            <p>But if you give us leave to make a <hi>cuſtome,</hi> and give us no power to preſſe the <hi>cuſtome,</hi> you doe as much in effect, as if you gave us a gift with one hand, and ſought with the other to ſnatch it from us.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> gives counſell to <hi>Lucinius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Lucin.</note> 
               <hi>that all the cuſtomes of the Church, that were no prejudice to the faith, ſhould be ſtrictly obſerved:</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> is ſo ſtiffe for the <hi>cuſtome</hi> here, that he will not ſuffer it to bee overborne by the ſtubborne humour of <hi>contentious men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> had ſuch a ſtroke in the firſt beginning and infancy of the Goſpell, when they could not be of many yeeres ſtanding, what power may belong unto them in theſe latter times, being now confirmed by long uſe, whereby they are become the more a <hi>cuſtome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no company nor ſociety of men but ſtand upon the right of their owne <hi>cuſtomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">All men ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owne cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</note> nay every pariſh, and private houſe is ready to lay claime to one or other; and when the <hi>Church</hi> her ſelfe hath taken up a <hi>cuſtome</hi> that tends to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of Gods ſervice, may not ſhe have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſtand upon it, and to binde her children to conformity?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:15930:26"/>
Could you but ſhew for your <hi>Civill cuſtomes,</hi> what we can alledge for our <hi>Church-cuſtoms,</hi> good leave may you have to ſtand upon them; but I doubt, by your favour, it will be long enough ere you can ſhew the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſeale for the warrant and juſtification of <hi>your cuſtomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some <hi>cuſtomes</hi> you have, I muſt needs grant, which you may ſafely hold by the ſame right, as being not <hi>determined by the written laws,</hi> of that nature are your <hi>Wayes,</hi> and <hi>Mounds,</hi> and <hi>fines,</hi> and <hi>quitrents,</hi> and <hi>ſuits,</hi> and <hi>ſervices,</hi> and <hi>commons,</hi> and <hi>releefes,</hi> and <hi>heriots,</hi> and 1000. more of the like kinde, that muſt be judged by the <hi>cuſtome,</hi> becauſe the Law therein hath preſcribed no certainty; but when you ſet up <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of your owne deviſing, which former ages never heard of, to ſtint the <hi>Church</hi> to a kinde of penſion, and to juſtle out the lawes in that caſe provided, well may you force us to ſuffer <hi>ſuch cuſtomes,</hi> but you ſhall never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us to allow them.</p>
            <p>The Lord foreſaw in his owne wiſdome that ſuch injurious <hi>cuſtomes</hi> were like to grow upon his owne law,<note place="margin">Lev. 27.28. &amp; 31.</note> and therefore he makes proviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, that if any had a minde <hi>to buy out their tithes for ready mony, they ſhould yeeld a fifth part over and above the reall value of the thing redeemed,</hi> to prevent ungodly compoſitions.</p>
            <p>If any <hi>cuſtome</hi> or <hi>compoſition</hi> of theſe times ſhall freely allow that <hi>fifth part over,</hi> well may they hold and enjoy their <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> but if they come ſhort of that proportion, as commonly they doe which are moſt urged, that ſcarce allow one <hi>fifth</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15930:27"/>for all the due; I trow every honeſt and well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed heart will firſt conſult with his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience how his plea will hold in the inner court, before he ſtand upon ſuch a <hi>cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such cuſtomes</hi> as theſe in their owne nature, as <hi>being delivered to us by word of mouth, beſide the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the word,</hi> are much alike to ſome <hi>Romiſh tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> which our adverſaries ſeeke to obtrude up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us: but if the word of God be ſufficient againſt the one, as I trow it is, I hope it may be thought as ſufficient againſt the other, and ſo the matter is ſoone agreed.</p>
            <p>Conſider I pray how God ſhall <hi>bleſſe the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of our hands,</hi> as long as wee ſeeke to <hi>binde his hands?</hi> how ſhall he vouchſafe to <hi>enlarge</hi> us, as long as we ſeeke to <hi>ſtraighten</hi> him? how can we looke for a <hi>full increaſe,</hi> while wee meane to allow him <hi>no increaſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not for me to cry downe theſe <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> wherin every one prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſome intereſt, but if you ſtand ſo much upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe upſtart <hi>cuſtoms,</hi> that tend to the hinderance of religion; I trow there is no man can thinke ill of us, if we plead hard for the ancient <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> that ſerve to the honour of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to the furtherance of <hi>Gods ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt needs know that <hi>Mos populi dei</hi> is a great deale more then <hi>Mos populi;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Church may ſtäd upon hers much more. <hi>Inſt. l 4. ca. 10. ſect. 30.</hi>
               </note> they are but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>humane cuſtoms</hi> that proceed from man &amp; tend to man; but the <hi>cuſtomes of the Church,</hi> that ſerve for the furtherance of devotion, if you pleaſe to beleeve Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelfe, are not only <hi>humane,</hi> but alſo <hi>divine,</hi> and ſo may the better be ſtood upon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15930:27"/>
You ſay well (may ſome reply) ſo they bee good and wholeſome <hi>cuſtomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt cuſtomes Ob. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but if they breed offence to the people of God, and may not bee kept with a ſafe conſcience, were they not better be taken away then maintained to breed more offence?</p>
            <p>To this objection let the wiſe <hi>Lawgiver</hi> make an anſwer:<note place="margin">Sol. Nulla lex ſatis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda omni bus, idton tum quari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c. <hi>Cat. apud Liv. decad. lib. 4.</hi> Singulos per dies n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant. <hi>Iren. lib. 1.</hi> Ob. <hi>2.</hi> Sol.</note> 
               <hi>There is no Law</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>profitable and commodious unto all; that is the thing to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whether it ſuit with the greater part;</hi> and if it be liked of the moſt and better part, wee muſt not alter <hi>a Law</hi> ſo generally allowed, to give content to a few humoriſts, that will hardly bee pleaſed with any <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But another will ſay, theſe pretended <hi>cuſtomes</hi> are a great impeachment to Chriſtian liberty.</p>
            <p>If any man think ſo, let<note n="*" place="margin">Inſt. l. 4. c. 10. ſupr: <hi>Ob.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> anſwer (if they will take his word) <hi>That the outward orders of the Church can lay no bond upon the conſcience, as long as they are no fixed and perpetuall laws, but externall ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of humane weakneſſe and infirmity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever they are may another ſay, as long as they deale in things indifferent, they may bee uſed indifferently, and not preſſed upon ſuch as cannot brooke them.</p>
            <p>I marry,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> if every one ſhould bee left to his owne will, when the <hi>Church</hi> hath agreed upon a rule,<note place="margin">Resalioquin per ſe mediae mutant quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammodo natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. <hi>Theſ. eccl. Belg. art. 6</hi>
               </note> we ſhould have a goodly <hi>Church</hi> in a ſhort time. <hi>Such a liberty (M. Calvin can tell you) could not chuſe but cauſe great confuſion, and that confuſion and diſorder could not chuſe but breed ſundry quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15930:28"/>
I,<note place="margin">Ob. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> but they need not be urged for all that with ſuch rigour and extremity, as if they were equall to the law of God.</p>
            <p>No,<note place="margin">Sol. Obligatio ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> coertione null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Aug.</hi> Iura n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a dicenda ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> God forbid it ſhould come to that yet: they muſt be urged upon ſome to make the bond ſo much the ſtronger. <hi>Give us a law without a bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power,</hi> and tis like a bell without a clapper: eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man will be ready to put it off like a ſlipper or pantofle at his pleaſure, ſo the <hi>Church</hi> her ſelfe &amp; all her <hi>cuſtomes</hi> ſhall become a ſcorn and by-word to <hi>contentious men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be ſome may urge further,<note place="margin">Ob. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> if your <hi>cuſtomes</hi> were ſuch as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſtands upon, none would deny them a <hi>binding power.</hi> Thoſe it ſeems were framed by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and generally allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the <hi>Churches;</hi> and if it were not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had never implyed ſo much by his <hi>(nos habemus, &amp; Eccleſiae Dei) we have them, and the Churches of God:</hi> whenſoever you make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that any of your <hi>cuſtomes</hi> were either <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or <hi>univerſally received</hi> of all the <hi>Churches,</hi> you ſhall finde us ready to ſubſcribe without more adoe, that we may not be thought to be <hi>contentious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether any of our <hi>cuſtomes</hi> be ſuch or no,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Ambr. in</hi> 4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> at leaſt if it were his ownwork. To. 3. tit. 7. cap. 63.</note> I dare not avouch upon any certainty: I heare St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> complaine in his time, that the <hi>Churches</hi> had ſwarved from the <hi>Apoſtolique cuſtomes;</hi> and <hi>Waldenſis</hi> likewiſe in his time, that the <hi>Apoſtolique traditions</hi> could hardly be diſcerned from ſuch as were meerely <hi>eccleſiaſticall:</hi> yet if the rule of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> goe for current, as tis allowed by ſome
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15930:28"/>of our beſt Divines,<note place="margin">Li. 4. cont. Don. ca. 23. Zuing. de bapt. Field li 4. ca. 21.</note> 
               <hi>that whatſoever hath been gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally obſerved in any age, and yet not preſcribed in any Councell, may be certainly beleeved to be Apoſtolicall.</hi> I ſee no reaſon but ſome of our owne <hi>cuſtomes</hi> which found ſuch generall allowance in the daies of our Fathers, <hi>whereof wee can find no beginning, neither in the Councels of the Church, nor in the writings of the Fathers,</hi> may ſafely paſſe for <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were to be wiſhed (if wiſhes might ſtand for good proofs) that all the <hi>cuſtomes of the Church</hi> were onely ſuch, and that nothing might be uſed in any one, but what were allowed by all the reſt: when <hi>antiquity</hi> and <hi>univerſality</hi> meet both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame <hi>cuſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. 118. ep. ad Jan. inſolentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimae eſt inſaniae. &amp;c.</note> they give ſuch credit and countenance to the practice of the <hi>Church,</hi> that no man can refuſe to joyne with us <hi>without ſuſpition of diſtraction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if our <hi>cuſtomes</hi> be not ſuch, have wee therefore no right to ſtand upon any, unleſſe they come home to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> conditions? I warrant you <hi>habemus talem</hi> will be ſufficient for a ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, though we cannot ſay, <hi>habemus candem:</hi> for neither the<note n="a" place="margin">Doct. Field, li. 4. c. 20. ut ſup.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtolique cuſtomes</hi> can bind us, nor any elſe that have been generall, unleſſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Church</hi> give free allowance; and ſeeing wee have the ſame power in things indifferent, the ſame I ſay to <hi>frame a cuſtome,</hi> the ſame if need be to<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tert. de vela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. virg.</hi> Caetera qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dë diſciplinae admittunt novitatem correctionis. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Aug. ep. ad Jan.</hi> vel emëdari oportet quod fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bat, vel inſtitui quod non fiebat.</note> 
               <hi>change a cuſtome,</hi> let not us diſpute any more ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>novelty</hi> or <hi>particularity</hi> of the <hi>cuſtome,</hi> but readily ſubmit to the <hi>Churches order</hi> without any further diſputation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15930:29"/>
Before the <hi>cuſtome</hi> was ordained, it was free for every one to put in a caveat; but when the rule is once ſetled, there is no further place for diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>a ſimple obedience without any ſpeciall inquiſition, in ſuch a caſe, is moſt abſolute:</hi> and if the <hi>Church</hi> can hardly erre, as you heard before, in the ordination of a <hi>cuſtome,</hi> why ſhould I doubt that I ſhould erre in yeelding obedience to the <hi>cuſtome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No argument holds againſt a <hi>cuſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cuſtome a good plea for matter of rite.</note> nay it is ſo far from that, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> makes the bare allegation of the <hi>cuſtome</hi> a ſpeciall argument of it ſelfe againſt <hi>innovation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many arguments had he uſed in the former verſes, ſome from<note n="*" place="margin">Ver. 13. Ver. 7. Ver. 14</note> 
               <hi>decency,</hi> ſome from <hi>authority,</hi> ſome from <hi>nature,</hi> according as the nature of the matter would beſt allow: and now being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſtrike home, and to ſet a barre againſt all reply, he brings them up to the <hi>Churches cuſtome,</hi> that if the reſt of his arguments could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, yet this might be ſure to enforce obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> thou haſt now taught us an eaſie way to put an end to all <hi>contention</hi> that ever ſhall ariſe concerning ceremonies, henceforth if any ſhall <hi>ſeeme contentious,</hi> wee ſhall not need to beat him downe either with <hi>Fathers,</hi> or <hi>Councels,</hi> or <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or <hi>Scriptures,</hi> no nor yet the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of other <hi>Churches;</hi> what ſhall wee need to goe about when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſhewed us a nearer way,<note place="margin">Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio patrum in 1. Con. Nicen.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let the <hi>cuſtome</hi> prevaile in the name of God, and let no man preſume to ſpeak againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:15930:29"/>
If any private man ſhall attempt in time to come to bring upon us a new <hi>cuſtome,</hi> either in <hi>praying,</hi> or <hi>preaching,</hi> or <hi>baptizing,</hi> or <hi>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> or <hi>marying,</hi> or <hi>burying,</hi> whatſoever it bee, or by whomſoever it bee allowed, wee will ſay no more then S. <hi>Paul</hi> does, <hi>Non habemus talem, wee have none ſuch:</hi> You may not ſet up a <hi>new cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide, if any ſhall ſeek to put down the old, whether in <hi>ſtanding,</hi> or <hi>kneeling,</hi> or <hi>croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> or <hi>bowing,</hi> or <hi>uncovering,</hi> or whatſoever elſe of the ſame alloy, that hath beene either preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in our <hi>booke of Canons,</hi> or religiouſly continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the reverend practice of our <hi>mother Churches,</hi> we ſhall need to ſay no more then S. <hi>Paul</hi> implies, <hi>habemus talem, we have ſuch a cuſtome</hi> allowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and you have no power to put it downe.</p>
            <p>Indeed <hi>cuſtome</hi> is a good plea for outward rite,<note place="margin">Cuſtome no good plea for matter of doctrine.</note> but for the doctrine of Gods worſhip, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the eſſence of religion, we muſt not plead a bare <hi>cuſtome.</hi> When any part of that gracious char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be called in queſtion by ſtubborne <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> we muſt not follow the <hi>cuſtomes of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr: ep. 63. &amp; ad Pomp: 78. &amp; ad Quint. 74.</note> 
               <hi>but the truth of God;</hi> nor muſt we regard <hi>what men have done, but what Chriſt hath ſaid for our direction. Ad legem &amp; teſtimonia, to the law and the teſtimonies</hi> muſt we goe for tryall, there muſt wee ſeeke for our direction; but for matter of rites, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſcipline, which are things in themſelves meerely arbitrary, and <hi>no where expreſſed in the word of God:</hi> we can never uſe a more ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative argument then S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath uſed in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15930:30"/>the words of my text, <hi>We have,</hi> or, <hi>we have not ſuch a cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very name of <hi>cuſtome</hi> hath ſome weight, becauſe the allowance of the <hi>Church</hi> is added to it, yet it is not the allowance of every <hi>Church,</hi> that takes up a rite of her owne head, contrary to the order of other <hi>Churches;</hi> but the unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of ſundry <hi>Churches</hi> agreeing in one, that gives the name and force of a <hi>cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſtand upon the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of one <hi>Church,</hi> much leſſe doth he urge it againſt all the reſt; but loe he ſtands upon the <hi>generall uſe</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtolique Churches,</hi> and urges the harmony of the <hi>moſt,</hi> againſt the <hi>private uſe</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth;</hi> to teach us that if any queſtion ſhould ariſe in time to come about the different orders of ſundry <hi>Churches,</hi> that wee could hardly know which to follow, we ſhould ever preferre the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> of the moſt, and ſpecially thoſe which are moſt <hi>Apoſtolique,</hi> before the private orders of ſome few that have degenerated from the rule.</p>
            <p>You ſee the nature of S. <hi>Pauls cuſtomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40. &amp; 26.</note> and what power you have to ſtand upon them; a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>cuſtome</hi> you cannot have, nor better authority to beare you out: I will but onely adde this one word more, that your <hi>cuſtomes</hi> bee decent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> ſurniſhed with all thoſe ſpeciall properties which S. <hi>Paul</hi> requires in every <hi>cuſtome,</hi> and then you come fully up to the Apoſtles <hi>(talis)</hi> you have a <hi>cuſtome</hi> I warrant you againſt all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; and <hi>if any man ſeeme to be contentious,</hi> you may ſafely plead it in open Court <hi>(habemus talem) we have ſuch a cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15930:30"/>
But I feare I ſhall exceed the time, and ſo break the <hi>cuſtome</hi> while I ſtand ſo long upon the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cuſtome;</hi> but if I have tyred the patience of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in tracing this <hi>ſtrange unuſuall argument,</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the blame may reſt upon them whoſe wilfull and ſtubborne oppoſitions have forced mee to breake my <hi>uſuall cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For moſt of you, this labour might be ſpared, for I have ſeene your <hi>order</hi> and approved it, but others there are of that croſſe and peeviſh ſpirit, that I thinke if S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe would ſupply this place, he could hardly win them to conformity.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Church</hi> ſtand upon her <hi>cuſtomes</hi> while ſhe will, the rulers of the <hi>Church</hi> obſerve the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> and all the <hi>Doctors</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> both old and new <hi>allow the cuſtome,</hi> yet they reſolve to hold their <hi>cuſtome,</hi> their <hi>cuſtome</hi> of wilfull contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>If any <hi>cuſtome</hi> at all goe downe with them, it muſt be the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of ſome <hi>forraigne Church: Great is Diana of the Epheſians,</hi> and they are apt enough to admire <hi>her cuſtomes;</hi> but for the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> of our owne <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sr. <hi>George Paul</hi> in the life of Archb: Whitgift. Apoc. 3.17 18, 19.</note> which all our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſo much renowne; <hi>and our very adverſaries themſelves account an honour to our reformation,</hi> they muſt not be allowed upon any tearmes.</p>
            <p>Alas <hi>poore Mother, thou ſayeſt thou art rich, and wanteſt nothing, and knoweſt not that thou art poore, and naked, and miſerable, and blinde,</hi> that thou canſt not judge of the leaſt <hi>cuſtome: Thou muſt buy thy gold of them if thou wilt be rich, and thy raiment of them, if thou wilt be cloathed, and thy eye-ſalve of them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15930:31"/>if thou wilt be cured of thy blindneſſe;</hi> and yet the moſt of them will freely confeſſe (if they are not too ingratefull) that they themſelves have been debtors unto thee, not onely for the light of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly truth, but for the helpe of outward ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>Did the fame of thy children never ſpread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Alps,</hi> or their glory beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the <hi>Lemanian lake?</hi> Why then ſhould thy children deſpiſe thy <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> and dote upon the love of <hi>forraign Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> unleſſe they meane to play the parts of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious children, to diſcredit the wombe that brought them forth, and the pappes that brought them up.</p>
            <p>For our parts, wee are loath to diſcredit our neighbour <hi>Churches,</hi> ſuch as have joyned with us in the reformation; whatſoever <hi>cuſtomes</hi> they have, we envy them not, good leave may they have to ſtand upon them, and if any of us ſhould converſe among them, we would not ſtick to uſe their <hi>cuſtomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rule that S.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apud Aug. ep. ad Caſulanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Quando Rome ſum, &amp;c. &amp; ad quamcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliam eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis ejus m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, ſi pari ſcanda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, nec vultis, aec facere. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> gave to his friend S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> when he aſked his opinion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſting on the Saturday, which was the <hi>cuſtom at Rome,</hi> but not at <hi>Millaine,</hi> that <hi>when hee was at Rome, he uſed to faſt, and when he was at Millaine hee uſed to eate;</hi> the ſame muſt we alwayes obſerve in matter of Rite, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teaches, <hi>If wee will neither offer nor ſuffer ſcandall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let mee give the counſell that<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier. ep. ad Lucin.</hi> Ego illud te breviter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monendum puto, &amp;c. Necalieru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſuetudi. nem ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contrario modo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verti.</note> 
               <hi>Ierome</hi> gave to his friend <hi>Lucinius, that thou keepe the cuſtomes of the Church inviolable, and ſuffer not the cuſtomes of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15930:31"/>one Church to be undermined, to bring in the cuſtomes of another.</hi> Thou maiſt eaſily offend either way, but chiefly in oppoſing thine owne <hi>Church:</hi> for if it be matter of ſcandall as you heard before, to refuſe the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of forraigne <hi>Churches</hi> whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we chance to communicate with them, how can we free our ſelves from cauſe of <hi>ſcandall,</hi> when we ſpurne at the rites of our owne <hi>Church,</hi> and refuſe to conforme to her <hi>authoriſed cuſtomes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt ſay no more of theſe kinde of men, for I doubt my doome is paſſed already; I muſt goe for a <hi>formaliſt,</hi> a <hi>time-ſerver,</hi> and I know not what if I plead ſo hard for the <hi>Churches cuſtome;</hi> but if I ſuffer in this cauſe, S. <hi>Paul</hi> may beſt anſwer for me, he hath deceived me if I be deceived, and if he have a ſhare in this hard cenſure, I ſhall bee well content to ſuffer with him, although they ſhould make me yet more vile.</p>
            <p>Howſoever it be, I ſhall yet intreat for all that, and I will not intreat in mine owne name, but in the words of the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Now I beſeech you brethren by the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that you all ſpeake one thing, and that there may be no ſchiſmes and diſſentions among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let no man ſtrive againſt the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> for that will turne to his owne confuſion, theſe warres <hi>are like the warres of Saul and David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam 3.1</note> 
               <hi>where the houſe of Saul grew ſtill weaker, and the houſe of David gathered ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is hard <hi>to kick againſt theſe pricks,</hi> for you may ſooner gall your owne feete by a fooliſh oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then you can blunt or ſpurne down the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cuſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:15930:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
There is neither comfort nor gaine in this raſh adventure, but onely the ſhame of your own <hi>mother;</hi> but if you will yeeld your ſelves like du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull children to obſerve the <hi>cuſtome,</hi> or like ſtout champions to plead the <hi>cuſtome,</hi> you have the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to defend you, and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of your Mother to encourage you, and the promiſe of your Father to reward you, even <hi>the Father of peace, and the Father of all comfort, who ſhall ſanctifie you all throughout, and keepe you both in ſoule and body, and ſpirit, blameleſſe untill the day of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
